AMELIE VOGEL

Copywriter Concept Designer

www.amelie-vogel.de

contact-amelievogel@gmail.com

ABOUT ME

Copywriter / Concept Designer

I am a copywriter experienced in micro-, short- and long copy. I also design user journeys and customer stories: in digital spaces for websites and interfaces as well as in analog spaces for brand experiences and company exhibitions.

The focus of my texts and concepts is always on the optimal user experience - from conception and planning to storytelling and the creation of content in text and visuals.

I think creatively and work pragmatically - independently and yet most productively in a team.

EXPERIENCE

real.digital: Editorial Department

February 2020 till today

I initiated and lead the project microcopy for the real.de online shop. I write microcopy and develop new UX-copy strategies: best practices that simplify the work of Product Designers and wording guidelines that focus on the customer and optimize the experience. I also write B2B and employer branding blog entries, postings for social media (Instagram and Facebook), and product guides.

,simple: Agency for Brand Experience

December 2018 till February 2020

For the creative agency ,simple, I freelance designed and created brand exhibitions and brand communication strategies. My client was the adidas-Archive and I did the conception of storytelling, user journey, and exhibition design. I also created the content and copywriting: long copy for the exhibition stories and UX-copy for the digital interfaces - in German and English. When the project ended, I had to find something new.

Web Development

Besides my work as a copywriter/concept designer, I worked as a freelance web developer and realized websites for cultural entrepreneurs. I am experienced in web development, web design, creating a streamlined user experience, and UX-copy.

Scientific Research

After studying German language and literature as well as art history (master's degrees), I was a Ph.D. student and did research on utopian urban planning as social engineering and spatial theory. I was able to publish several scientific texts. I enjoyed working in the agency more, so I gave up my dissertation in spring 2019 to focus on concept design and copywriting.

EDUCATION

University of Cologne

2013-2017

Master's degrees in art history and German language and literature, grade: 1.3.

University of Cologne

2009-2013

Bachelor's degrees in art history and German language and literature.

FREELANCE PROJECTS

adidas

2018 bis 2020 - Concept Design, Content Creation and Copywriting

For the brand exhibition of the adidas-Archive I developed concepts for exhibition design and storytelling, researched the content, and implemented the stories in multimedia and digital form (image, video, interfaces, and exhibition design). I also wrote long, short, and UX-copy in German and English.

Research assignment on the Structuralist Megastructure

2018 bis 2019 - scientific research

For the project "Perspektiven der Denkmalpflege", funded by the state of Nordrhein-Westfalen, I have been commissioned to conduct research on the influence of structuralist architecture and spatial planning on 20th-century spatial theory. I gave lectures and published articles.

SKILLS

Copywriting

I write in these areas: UX-copy, short copy, long copy, scientific writing, journalistic writing, social media, SEO-optimized writing - in German and English.

Conception Design

I design in these areas: user experience and user journeys, customer stories, brand strategies, and brand exhibitions. I love working agile and I utilize prototyping and Design Thinking.

Content Creation

I create in these areas: visuals and text. I also do content research for content creation.

Design

I design with this software: Adobe Photoshop, InDesign, InVision, and Figma.

Web Development

I work with these technologies: HTML and CSS.

Languages

German is my mother tongue and I studied German language and literature. I am also fluent in written and spoken English.